Anthropic just dropped its newest AI model called Clod 3.5 Sonnet, but it's not
quite
giving Shakespeare yet.
Anthropic is a rival of OpenAI, the company that makes ChatGPT.
That's some steep competition, and the pressure to keep pushing new updates is
strong.
The Sonnet model can analyze text and images, as well as generate text, and its
ability
to analyze charts and graphs has gotten significantly better with this update.
But the progress is only incremental, which makes sense, because this technology
is really
complicated and takes a long time to develop responsibly.
Try telling that to your investors, though.
TechCrunch reporter Kyle Wiggers said that while Sonnet looks really good on
paper, the
benchmarks that companies use to measure progress in AI sometimes aren't that
meaningful.
These models are often tested on esoteric edge cases, like the kinds of
questions you'd
find in a PhD-level math class.
But most people are using these chatbots for much simpler tasks, like writing
cover letters.
There's value in an AI being able to do that.
There's value in being able to explain post-doc chemistry research, but maybe
not
every AI needs to be good at everything.
If you're a historical researcher, for example, maybe you don't need an AI
trained on medical
information.
As for what else is new with Sonnet, Anthropic is working on Artifacts, which is
a workspace
where users can edit and add to content that they've already generated with
Claude.
The company wants to build this out to help teams collaborate, which points
toward Anthropic's
interest in attracting enterprise-level clients.
So far, that's an area where OpenAI has a lot of potential.
An executive at OpenAI disclosed last month that 93% of Fortune 500 companies
have enterprise-level
subscriptions to ChatGPT, but we don't know how much those companies are
actually using
it on a day-to-day basis.
The release of the Sonnet model could be a sign that generative AI is entering
its iterative
era and growth is slowing down or becoming more predictable.
AI might seem cutting edge, but it's repeating the same problems that we see
across the tech
industry.
Investors want to see profits faster than ever.
They want to see more money coming in.
They're more interested in the future than the technology can actually keep up.
Seed-level venture funding for generative AI startups declined in the new year
and that
could be because this expensive technology isn't yielding the returns that
investors
want yet.