as i get older i realize money is not everything but it's kind of almost
everything so every year
or every other year i download all my bank transactions and review my incomes
and expenses
the other day i came across someone who made this income and expense breakdown
and i feel
really inspired to do the same usually the most tricky thing in the process is
to classify the
expenses from my buying transactions into appropriate categories a lot of times
i just
use my manual labor or some low-tech ways to do that this year i decided to ask
chat to pt
to crunch the number for me and maybe tell me when i can retire only then to
realize that i can't
just upload my bank statement to chat tbt website it's all sensitive information
about places i've
been to shops i visited how much i spent on buying secret items and other
personal data although
using open ai apis may help still the data sent via the api is stored
by openai for a duration of up to 30 days so eventually i decided to download
and run an
open source large language model locally on my laptop and the best thing yet
they are free in
this project video we do a few exciting things first we learn to install and run
an lm for
example llama 2 locally on our laptop then we use the lm to classify all the
expenses in my
bank statement into categories such as groceries rent travel and so on we then
analyze the data in
python and create some visualizations to show the main insights i shared all the
codes on github so
you can check out the github repo in the video description this video is
sponsored by coursera
coursera is running a discount with 200 off the coursera plus annual
subscription if you sign
up this is half the regular price for the whole year with this subscription you
can get access
to the course you can also use the course you can also use the course you can
also use the course
course you can also use the course you can also use the course you can also use
the course you can also use
to tons of courses and certificates in data analytics, including the Google Data
Analytics
and the Google Advanced Data Analytics Certificates. These certificates teach
you
all the fundamentals you need as a beginner in data analytics. So check out the
offer below.
There are a few different ways to run a large language model locally on your
laptop,
which means you can run the LLM without internet connection, without a third-
party service like an
API service or a website like ChatGPT. As you can imagine, this is secure if you
want to protect
your personal data, and it's free. There are now a few different frameworks
developed to help us
run an open-source language model locally on our own device. Some popular
frameworks are LLM-CPP,
GPT-4-0, and OLAMA. So you might be wondering, why the heck do we even need
these frameworks?
Remember how large language models are trained? They're basically the result of
taking a huge
amount of internet data and train a large neural network on it. And the model
that comes out is
basically a zip file with a bunch of numbers that represents the weights of all
the parameters in
the neural network. This model file can be quite large, depending on how many
parameters the model
has. So frameworks like OLAMA and LLAMA-CPP basically try to do two things. The
first thing
is quantization. It tries to reduce the memory footprint of the raw model
weights. And the
second thing is it makes it more efficient to run an open-source language model
locally on your
device. So if you have a Mac or Linux machine, I'd highly recommend installing
OLAMA. It's super
simple, and I'll show you in a bit. If you have a Windows machine, you can also
run OLAMA through
the Docker desktop. Okay, now let's go to OLAMA website. And here you can
download OLAMA, which
is available for Mac OS and Linux, and Windows will be coming soon. Also have a
quick look at
the list of models that are available. So here we have LLAMA 2, Maestro,
we have a bunch of other code models. And so there's a lot of options here for
you to try out.
And if we click on any of them, we can see the description, also how to use API,
what is the
memory requirements, so how much RAM you need in your laptop in order to run
these models.
So let's download OLAMA and install it. It's very straightforward, just like
installing any app on
your laptop. So once we've installed OLAMA, we can start using it through our
terminal. In order to
do a language model locally through OLAMA, we just need to run the command
OLAMAPOOL and then specify
the model that you want to install. So for example, I will install again
Maestro. It's pretty fast
because I've already installed it last time. So and you can see here the model
is around 4GB. So
in order to use a model through a terminal, we just need to do OLAMA run
Maestro. And here we
can start typing our message or our prompt. So let's say hello, and the model
replied with Hello,
how can I help you today? Oh, so that's a lot of things. Okay, so I can ask
something a little bit
stupid. What's 2 plus 2? Okay, it comes back with quite an elaborate answer.
Now, let's try another
question. I want to see if it actually can do math properly. Let me ask what's
this times this. Okay,
wow, that's amazing. Okay, it even tries to teach me how to find the product of
two large numbers
so let me go to Google. Okay, so what I have here is around 426 billion.
However, if I look at the
result here, it's actually not correct. 45 million. You can check this result
using a calculator to
make sure it's correct. Well, I've checked it and it's not correct. I kind of
have to say I'm
impressed. But in terms of basic arithmetic, I think large language models out
of the box are
not probably not the best option. All right, the next thing we want to test,
that is very important for this project, is whether the Maestro model can
properly classify
all the different expenses in my bank statement into different categories. So I
just try out a
prompt here to see how it performs. Now, I ask, can you add an appropriate
category to the following
expenses? For example, Spotify as entertainment, beta photos as sports, and here
I just give a list
of transactions as shown in my bank statement. So let's see what it comes up
with.
Okay, so it replies with three categories. It's roughly correct. I would say
it's reasonable,
but it missed one transaction here, which is Bistro Bar Amsterdam. And also, it
doesn't really reply
in the format that I wanted. So the transaction together with the category
separate by this
hyphen. So I feel like Maestro, it doesn't really do the task as I expected it
to do. So let's try
Lama2. Let's exit this model and we will Olama run Lama2. But if you haven't
installed Lama2,
you can do Olamapool Lama2 and the Lama2 model will be installed locally in your
computer.
Now, we can start using Lama2 model. Now, let's ask the same question as we
asked before. And
it does it pretty well. It gives me a list of the expenses together with the
categories. Although,
the first two are my own example, but it does
give me the correct format for the answers and so each of these transactions has
a category
added next to it separated by a hyphen so i'm pretty happy with llama2 and it
actually
understands the task although if you keep asking the same question to these
language models multiple
times these models may come back with different answers each time and so there's
definitely a
certain level of randomness in the responses if you want to take a step further
to customize these
language models to your specific use case you can do that by specifying a model
file and a
model file is basically the blueprint to create and share language models with
olama so you can
specify the base model you want to use and also you can set parameters like the
temperature for
the model now let's go back to the terminal and exit this model let's clear the
terminal
and i'll go ahead and create a model file with nano and i'll name this model
file as
expense analyzer and we'll go into the text editor okay let's first specify the
base model as
llama2 so from llama2 and next we'll set the temperature parameter as let's say
0.8 temperature
closer to 1 is more creative and the lower the temperature the more coherent and
less creative
the model behaves and further let's also specify the custom system message so my
system prompt is
quite basic if you're a financial assistant
you have classified expense and income from buying transactions okay let's save
this file by ctrl x
yes enter now that we have the model file set up we can use this model file to
create a custom model
we can do this by olama create we specify the custom model name dash f and then
specify the name
of the model file so that is pens analyzer so now if we run this comment
basically what it's doing
is that olama will pass through this text file this model file expands analyzer
passing through
all the parameters and the custom message that we put in and then customize all
these different
layers in the base model which is lama2 and now we can start using this custom
lama2 model that
we just created by olama run expense analyzer i also forgot to mention that we
can also now
uh look at the model list available by olama list and you can also muito les
take a look at the model list available by olama list and you can also also find
out the base model
that we all엔 used to make custom models
also see that now we have the expense analyzer llama2 model available in our
list now interacting
with these local elements through the terminal is also fine but i find a more
convenient way to
interact with these models is through the python environment and more
specifically through jupyter
notebook now let's create a project folder and i'll move my bank transaction
data in inside this
folder and i'll just start up visual studio code from this folder in order to
access these language
models from olama with python we need to install the langchaincommunity library
and so if you
haven't done so we can use pip install and now we can access all the language
models we have
installed through olama by specifying the name of the model with this olama
method for example the
first man on the moon was dot dot dot and after a few seconds we get back the
completion of this
sentence so that means our model is up and running that is a good sign now let's
move on to reading
that milky way of thinking so that means our model is up and running that is a
good sign now let's move on to reading that austin will 19606 now let's move on
to reading that austin will 19606
transaction data that we have and take a look at it you can see that here in the
name description
column we have all the transactions that we want to classify we have the
indicator whether it is
expense or income and we also have the amount in euros of these transactions now
i have anonymized
a lot of these transactions so this is not my real income and real expenses now
we need to find a way
to insert all these different expenses into our prompt right let's get all the
unique transactions
from our data you can see that this is quite a big list and this may exceed the
token limit that the
large language model has so if we try to insert this huge list into our prompt
there's a risk
that the model comes back with a completely nonsensical answer or incomplete
answer because
your question is already taking too many tokens so after many trial and errors i
found that around
two and a half minutes or so we have a lot of questions that we can answer and
we can't answer
30 transactions would give the most optimal response so here you can see an
example response
with 30 transactions so with this approach we are going to create a for loop to
basically loop
through all the 300 transactions here in our bank statement and we take in 30
transactions at a time
and so a handy way to handle this for loop is to get an index list so this index
list is basically
giving us a sequence of all the index from zero until the last item hopping 30
items at a time
and with this we can also conveniently handle the last group as well which might
not be 30 items but
maybe less now let's initialize a data frame to store all the unique
transactions and their
responding categories and with this for loop our call a custom function that i
created and this
function takes the names of the transactions or the lm that we are using and the
only thing we
need to do is to
properly parse the output from the language model into a format that we can work
with. So if we look
at this output, we definitely only want to keep these lines, right? And we don't
want the rest
like certainly here's the categories. But we don't need to worry about this for
now because at the
end, we can always remove all the rows that have categories being none. The
complication is that
sometimes the language model might use a different format for the answer. So we
had to use some kind
of like validator for the output in order to make sure that the output actually
is in the format we
want. For example, in the response, we have the hyphen in between the
transaction and the category.
So one handy Python library for this is Pydantic. So the idea is that after
getting the response,
we will run it through a validation check. If the validation fails, we will
rerun the language model
to get another response until we get the right output. If you're interested in
how to do this
with Pydantic, you can click on the link in the description below. And if you're
interested in
the code in the GitHub repo, link in description. Okay, now let me run this for
loop and also print
out the transaction names and also the output by the models. I also noticed that
when I'm running
this for loop, for some reason, if I want to stop it, I really cannot stop it.
So if for some reason
we want to interrupt this process, we can go to the terminal and do pqolama. And
so in the back
end, all the olama processes will be stopped. Okay, after a while, if everything
goes well,
we should get back the data frame.
Okay, so now we're done with all the transactions with the categories that Lama2
has categorized for
us. I'll just save the CSV here. Now let's open the CSV file and quickly look at
the output.
Overall, I'm quite happy with the categories that Lama2 came up with. However,
some categories
may be quite similar to each other, but not completely the same. And I want to
group them
together. So I just quickly group these categories by hand. Now the last step is
to clean up a little
bit this data frame. And then we can go ahead and merge this data frame. And
then we can go ahead and
my data frame into the main transaction data frame using the transaction name.
So after this,
we should have a data frame with all information, the transactions and the
categories. So that was
exciting. But the next part of the project is even more exciting. We create a
personal finance
dashboard based on the transaction data that we just obtained. The idea for this
dashboard is we
want to show the income breakdown and the expense breakdown for both years 2022
and 2023. And at the
bottom i also want to show how much i earn and how much i spend per month in
each year so for creating
interactive visualization i love using plotly express for the creation of the
dashboard we also
use panel panel is an awesome library for creating data dashboard very easily
and very fast now let's
read in our transaction data and for the income i don't have a lot of income
sources so i can just
use the name of the income as the category firstly we want to make the pie chart
to show the income
and expense breakdown i create a function here to basically take the data and
select for the year
and whether we are looking at the expense or the income in the data set and
similarly i also create
a function to make bar charts that basically gives us a histogram of the income
or expense
per month over the year and you can see that it's super nice
with plotly express that you can also hover on the different sections on the
graph and see the
data label now we're almost done we just need to combine and organize all these
charts on our
dashboard so here just create a panel layout with the tabs which consists of two
tabs we have the
2022 for 2023 tab we have exactly the same charts and graphs but for 2023 data
and to show all this
nicely on the dashboard we will use a template from
our dashboard which is called fastlist template we can specify the header of our
dashboard
we have the sidebar which is some information and also you can put in different
elements or pictures
etc and in the main here we will put in the tabs that we just created and if we
do template show
we can see that this is our dashboard and here's my income and expense breakdown
and here is how
much i earned and how much i spent per month in each year you can see that i do
a little bit more in 2022 than in 2023 which is not really a good sign but if
you're into personal
finance and things like that you may notice that this overview is probably not
complete because we
also have assets so if you transfer your money to an investment account or if
you pay the mortgage
towards your house then part of that money is also your asset as well and not
only your expense
although as you can see i can't retire anytime soon i hope this inspires you to
do your own
projects and experiment with open source language models i think in the future
it will be a norm for
us to be able to use and run large language models locally on laptops and other
personal devices if
you enjoyed this project also check out other data science projects on my
channel thank you for
watching bye