Is prompt engineering really going to take over software engineering?
Well, for one thing, the president and co-founder of NVIDIA says this is going
to happen.
Okay, let me explain. Jensen Huang, who is the president and co-founder of
NVIDIA,
recently went on to the World Government Summit in Dubai and here's what he
said.
He said that his statement that he was about to share is what most tech
influential people
have said over the last 10 or 15 years, which is that everyone, especially kids,
should learn how to code. So here's what he said though. He goes on to say,
it is our job to create computing technology that nobody has to program
and that the programming language is human. Then he goes on to say,
everyone in the world is now a programmer. This is the miracle of AI.
All right, before we dive into this topic further and really break down,
is software engineering getting replaced by prompt engineering? Make sure to hit
the subscribe button for more tech, future tech, career, all the above topics
and leave in the
comments any other questions or topics you want me to cover. All right, now
let's get into it.
This is a really bold statement to make. And I think a lot of people,
if you are someone who is learning to code or just getting into tech, it will
feel very
discouraging because of this statement. I mean, I know for myself, when I was
learning how to code,
I was doing so during the boom of coding, if you will, meaning it was just
endless opportunities
and possibilities with this skill. And it was one of the hardest things I had to
learn,
but it was so rewarding. Now to see that this skill is something that might not
be learned or
as valuable, or people don't tout as people don't look up as this really great
skill.
It really brings a lot of different emotions my way. Now I'm going to keep my
emotions out of
this video and really dive into the facts. So if you are someone who is learning
how to code,
getting into tech, or maybe you are an engineer, this video is for you. Now
let's start off with
the obvious. Jensen is not the first individual, especially of a high caliber to
be sharing these
statements. But for some reason, this time it felt different. I've heard a lot
of these statements
of how AI is going to take over programming, and I never really paid much
attention to it.
But this statement from him, I think it's because it feels so different because
we are at a time
where we can see that this could become a reality. Now here's the thing. I don't
want this video to
dissuade anyone or discourage anyone from learning to code. There is going to be
some really great
opportunities for you still, if you are in that boat. But what I think is a
bigger question here,
and what we really should look at rather than should you learn how to code
anymore,
or should you not learn how to code anymore, is what this
bigger picture here. Let's take a step back. I was going to take a step back
literally,
but the chair is in the way. And really say, see, what exactly does this mean?
Well, for one thing,
it means we are coming into a period of time that's never been done in history
before where
technology is advancing quicker than we can keep up with it. We are not able to
keep up on a daily
basis with the tech advancements anymore as humans. So yes, that can sound a
little bit scary
on one hand, but on the other hand, what it really is showing is you need to not
be comfortable in
your role, in your current skill sets, but being open to continue to evolve.
All right, Tiff, can you just cut to the chase? Is prompt engineering going to
replace software
engineers? No, it's not, at least not for the foreseeable future, but things are
going to change
drastically. And I mean, we already see this with how much now we are using AI
in our daily lives
when coding. Think of tools like Copilot or different, even ChatGPT when you are
coding,
you are now able to go into these artificial intelligent chatbots and ask for
help, get
suggestions at a quicker rate than you would have if you were a software
engineer. So, if you are
a software engineer, you are going to be able to do this much faster than ever
before.
Let's start though by breaking down what exactly is a prompt engineer. At its
core,
prompt engineering focuses on creating and designing prompts that are given to
AI models.
I mean, we always talk about ChatGPT to really instruct them to have the desired
outputs. So,
why is this role important? I think at first it was really laughed at as, oh,
this role is going
to come and go, but the more we grow with AI, the more we can realize that this
role is here to stay
and becoming more and more important. What sets prompt engineers apart? Well,
a lot of prompt engineers have a very strong background in machine learning or
artificial
intelligence. They are aware of how these models operate, how it will affect
them,
what they input into these models based on what they output and get, and they're
very
knowledgeable in that area. Now, that's not saying you have to have knowledge
around machine learning
or AI to become a prompt engineer, but at some level you do need to start diving
into it.
The other thing about prompt engineers is depending on what company they are
working for,
they usually are specialists within that industry. So, for example, prompt
engineering is something
that is widely used within the health industry. And if you are a prompt engineer
working in health
and trying to diagnose someone or have some understanding as to what ailments
they have,
you need to also have an understanding as to the health side of this industry.
You can't just be
this technical person. Okay, so here is the role of a prompt engineer broken
down pretty simply
for you. So, one, you have to design effective prompts. Two, refine and
optimize, so continuously
test and refine your prompts to ensure you're getting the best output. Number
three is customize
your prompts to fit particular projects or industries. This is kind of what we
spoke to
a little bit earlier, that you need to be, to some degree, an expert in that
field. And number four
is monitor outputs. So, ensure that the outputs are what is expected, that the
AI model isn't
hallucinating, and there isn't anything else weird going on there. All right, so
let's take a look at
how artificial intelligence has already impacted software engineering. Well, for
one thing, we
mentioned earlier, now we have code assistants. So, we have things such as
Copilot, who will now
write out tire intelligence. So, we have things such as Copilot, who will now
write out tire
intelligence. So, we have things such as Copilot, who will now write out entire
functions, entire
files for you or with you. The next is debugging and code review. Now, we have
tools that can help
you debug and also review your code, which is super helpful if you are someone
who is working
on a team. Next up, we have tools to automate documentation. I mean,
documentation is probably
one of the worst parts of software engineering, in my opinion, anyways. Who
wants to deal with
documentation? But having AI to help write documentation for you based on your
code
is a game changer. One of the tools I actually used,
quite a while ago and love, not sponsored, just shouting them out, is Swim. So,
Swim will actually
help generate documentation based on your files in your GitHub, which is, it's
really cool.
Anyway, so that's already exists too. Next is ideation and problem solving. So,
providing new approaches or algorithms for solving complex problems. I mean,
what is left for programmers? We just went through everything that AI can do.
The reality is,
even if prompt engineering takes over software engineering, which, let's do a
side note here,
doesn't mean software engineering doesn't exist. We're not having that
conversation. Of course,
it's going to exist. Say prompt engineering does grow and become more in demand
than a role like
software engineers. The reality is, A, if you are a software engineer growing
into a prompt
engineering role, or even staying in your software engineering role, it will
just start looking
different over time. We are in the weeds with this. We're not going to see this
happen directly
overnight. Although it does feel like it's happening very quickly. It's more so
being able
to use these AI tools, implement AI tools, and use them to solve complex
problems. So,
implement it into your workflow, and you are going to be fine. Going back to
what the president
and co-founder of Nvidia said, he also goes on to say that it's important for
people to learn
how to use generative AI. So, it will be vital that we upskill everyone. And the
upskilling
process, I will be delightful and surprising. He's very optimistic. But to his
point,
it is going to be more and more vital that we continue to get more comfortable
with these
generative AI tools versus saying, we are too good for them. We're not going to
use them.
The reality is they are here and they're here to stay. Okay. So,
to the chase, is prompt engineering going to overtake software engineering?
There will always
be a place for software engineers and there will always be a place for prompt
engineers. But I do
see that these two roles will merge closer and closer together. I mean, prompt
engineering will
merge with many different roles. And I do believe software engineering is one of
them. All right.
I'm curious to hear, do you agree with my thoughts? Do you disagree? I try and
stay
pretty neutral on this because the reality is we don't know what we don't know.
And the
most important takeaway is being open to continuous learning and not...
freaking out like that meme where the dog is standing with a cup and
everything's blowing
up around him. All right. Thank you all for watching and make sure to hit that
subscribe
button for more tech, future tech, news, all of the above. And I'll see you
soon. Thanks everyone.