Welcome to Netflix Creative Labs. In this episode, we'd like to take you back
into
the world of machine learning, where it continues to revolutionize our industry.
My name is Kelly Griggs. My name is Anish Bhattakavi. Here at Netflix, the
utilization of machine learning has significantly changed the way we work.
Algorithms are used in various fields, including mathematics, computer science,
and everyday problem-solving. This tool simplifies the process for building
machine learning models. The core idea is that anyone can train a machine
learning model. All you have to do is spend some time in our tool and label
some examples as positive or negative. Imagine having to sift through over 1
million movies with over 2 billion shots to organize and categorize. It's a
daunting task, but we have found a solution that can streamline the process.
The ingredients or building blocks of our content understanding, simplified, is
a binary human in-the-loop approach to machine learning classification. Any
one can simply click positive or negative for the examples presented, thus
strengthening the algorithm's classification. Some users have called it
fun and addictive, which are not adjectives you usually hear about data
annotation. Our video annotator tool is an excellent example of how Netflix
leverages machine learning. We can train algorithms faster and have more time to
actually get creative. We want to show people their favorite moments when that
moment arrives.
Learn more at Netflix.com.
Techblog.com, the future of creativity.